Susan Finlay Watkins Collection of Textile Related Graphics 6902 G
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Susan Finlay Watkins Collection of Textile Related Graphics
1783
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Watkins, Susan Finlay
6902 G
0.11 cubic feet
0.1 linear ft.
Engraving.
Series of 12 engravings by William Hincks that illustrate the various stages of the preparation of linen in Ireland.
10079353
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
R. Miles, October 16, 2017
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, December 11, 2017
Biographical / Historical
William Hincks was born in Waterford, Ireland. He was a self-taught artist, creating portraits in crayon, oils, and chalk. While in Dublin in 1780, Hincks illustrated an edition of "Tristram Shandy." His twelve-plate series on linen production was originally published in 1782. It was later republished in 1791 by R. Pollard, Spafields, London.
Scope and Contents
Series of 12 engravings that illustrate the various stages of the preparation of linen in Ireland, from sowing the flax seed to the sale of the bleached cloth. Original engravings published by Hincks in London in 1783. Date of this reproduction is unknown.
William Hincks delin. et sculp. (drawn and engraved by William Hincks).
Plate VIII is missing from this set.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 6902: Susan Finlay Watkins Collection of TWUA Documents
Flax; Linen; Textile manufacturers -- Ireland; Textile machinery; Textile workers; Ireland; Hincks, William (1794-1871)
10079353
- Linen Production in Ireland, 1783 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Item 1: This View taken near Scarva in the County of Downe, representing Ploughing, Sowing the Flax Seed and Harrowing, 1783; Graphics (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Plate I. Engraving. Image shows farmer harrowing field with four horses; man on right sows flax seed. Several women and children sit in lower left foreground; house visible in upper left background. 49.5 x 42.5 cm.
  - Item 2: This View taken near Hillsborough in the County of Downe, representing Pulling the Flax when grown, Hooking or putting it up to Dry, Ripling or saving the Seed, and Boging or burying it in Water, 1783; Graphics (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Plate II. Engraving. Image shows flax being pulled from the ground (right background); in foreground a woman draws the flax through a ripple (large metal comb) to remove the seed; in the foreground a man places the flax in water to soak it. Landscape is very romantic; church steeple visible in left background. 49.5 x 42.5 cm.
  - Item 3: This View taken in the County of Louth Representing taking the Flax out of the Bog when it has lain a sufficient time to seperate the Rind, (which is the Flax) from the Stem & strengthen it, spreading it to dry, stoving, beetling, and breaking it, 1783; Graphics (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Plate III. Engraving. Image shows a man in the foreground removing the flax from the water. In the center, a woman lays bundles of flax over a hot kiln to dry them; a man beats the flax bundles. 49.5 x 42.5 cm.
  - Item 4: This Plate, representing the common Method of Beetling, Scutching and Hackling the Flax..., 1783; Graphics (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Plate IV. Engraving. Image shows a young woman seated on the left beetling the flax; the woman seated on the left is scutching the flax with a long wooden blade as is the woman on the right in the background. The man on the right is drawing the flax through a series of blocks containing different size hackle pins to remove any pieces of straw from the flax. 49.5 x 42.5 cm.
  - Item 5: This Plate representing a Perspective View of a Scutch Mill, with the Method of Breaking the Flax with groved Rollers, and Scutching it with Blades fixt on a Shaft, both turn'd by the Main Wheel, 1783; Graphics (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Plate V. Engraving. Image shows water wheel that turned the scutching blades (visible in left background). Woman with child in left foreground; man seated in right foreground. 49.5 x 42.5 cm.
  - Item 6: This Plate, taken on the spot in the County of Downe, Representing Spinning, Reeling with the Clock Reel, and Boiling the Yarn, 1783; Graphics (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Plate VI. Engraving. Image shows young woman at left and elderly woman in center right spinning flax yarn. Woman at right winds yarn on clock reel. Woman in background boils the yarn in a pot over the fire. 49.5 x 42.5 cm.
  - Item 7: This Plate, representing Winding, Warping with a new improved Warping Mill, and Weaving, 1783; Graphics (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Plate VII. Engraving. Image shows man in center winding yarn off a rack of bobbins onto a warp mill by using a pulley. The weaver at left is using a simple treadle loom and a curved shuttle. The boy in the background is winding pirns on a prin winder. 49.5 x 42.5 cm.
  - Item 8: This Plate representing a complete Perspective View of all the machinery of a bleach mill, upon the Newest and most approved Constructions, consisting of the Wash Mill, Rubbing Boards moved by a Crank, and Beetling Engine for Glazing the Cloth, with a Vie, 1783; Graphics (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Plate IX. Engraving. Image shows a worker in the foreground twisting the cloth to get the moisure out ?); worker on the right is finishing (?) the cloth. 49.5 x 43 cm.
  - Item 9: This Perspective View of a Bleach Green taken in the County of Downe, Shewing the methods of Wet & Dry Bleaching, and the outside View of a Bleach Mill, on the most approved construction, 1783; Graphics (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Plate X. Engraving. Image shows cloth laid out on a village green (regularly watered, this was wet bleaching) with workers soaking the cloth in a trough; bleach mill visible on side of river; young couple in foreground. 50 x 43 cm.
  - Item 10: This Plate representing a Perspective View of a Lapping Room, with the Measuring, Crisping or Folding the Cloth in Lengths, Picking the Laps or Lengths, Tying in the Clips, acting by the Mechanic power of the Laver to press the Cloth round & firm, and Sea, 1783; Graphics (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Plate XI. Engraving. Image shows linen cloth being folded and pressed by workers. 50 x 43 cm.
  - Item 11: This Perspective View of the Linen Hall in Dublin with the Boxes and Bales of Linen ready for Exportation, the Emblems of their Industry, 1783; Graphics (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Plate XII. Engraving. Image shows the exterior of the LInen Hall in Dublin, Ireland, where bales and boxes of linen cloth were ready for exportation. 49.5 x 43 cm.